Luca Di Stefano

Curriculum vitae January 2022

Personal information

E-mail: luca.di-stefano@inria.fr

Work address: 655 avenue de l'Europe, 38334 Montbonnot, France

Web page: convecs.inria.fr/people/Luca.Di-Stefano/

Research interests

My research mainly concerns the formal modelling and analysis of agent-based models of complex collective systems. On one hand, this entails the development of formally defined high-level languages to concisely describe the features of individual agents; on the other hand, it requires applying and improving state-of-the-art verification techniques to check the collective behaviour of the resulting system.

Keywords associated with my interests include:

Modelling: Agent-based modelling, Attribute-based communication, Collective adaptive systems, Domain-specific languages, Multi-agent systems, Process algebras, Stigmergic interaction, Structural operational semantics, Temporal logics.

Analysis: Bounded model checking, Explicit-state and symbolic model checking, Software verification, Static analysis.

Education

Gran Sasso Science Institute

L'Aquila, Italy

PhD in Computer Science November 2016 – October 2020

Thesis: Modelling and Verification of Multi-Agent Systems via Sequential Emulation

Advisors: Rocco De Nicola, Omar Inverso **URL**: hdl.handle.net/20.500.12571/10181

Other activities: Student representative in the academic senate (2018–2020).

University of L'Aquila

L'Aquila, Italy

MSc in Computer Science and Systems Engineering March 2014 – October 2016 **Thesis**: Design of a reactive system for autonomous UAV navigation in unknown environments. Thesis written in Italian. Original title: *Progettazione di un sistema reattivo per la navigazione autonoma di un drone in ambienti sconosciuti*.

Advisors: Eliseo Clementini, Enrico Stagnini

Final grade: 110/110, cum laude

Official degree name: Ingegneria Informatica e Automatica.

Positions held

CONVECS, Inria/LIG

Grenoble, France

Post-doctoral researcher

November 2020 – Present time

The aim of this post-doc is to enable efficient model checking of temporal properties in the context of collective adaptive systems. Building upon previous work with the CONVECS team, I developed an automated translation of a state-based temporal property language into MCL (an extension of the alternation-free fragment of the modal μ -calculus), and used it to verify a selection of systems. I am also investigating how compositional verification techniques may help with model checking of large systems.

SySMA, IMT Lucca

Lucca, Italy

Grant holder

December 2019 – October 2020

The grant topic was "Verification of Emerging Properties in Collective Adaptive Systems". I adapted a structural encoding procedure I had been working upon as part of my PhD to multiple verification tools implementing a variety of techniques, including predicate abstraction, *k*-induction and property-directed reachability.

CONVECS, Inria/LIG

Grenoble, France

Visiting PhD student

March – July 2019

As a visitor at CONVECS I focussed on topics related to my thesis, such as defining a structural encoding of multi-agent systems in the LNT specification language and using it to verify these systems through model checking.

Teaching

Polytech Paris-Saclay

Paris, France

MSc course in Modelling and Verification

April – May 2021

36-hour course for Master students in Computer Science Engineering, *filière apprentissage*. Held remotely as a supply teacher (*intervenant vacataire*). The course focused on the following topics: modelling of concurrent systems through communicating automata (labelled transition systems); behavioural equivalences; process algebras (CCS, LNT); modal and temporal logics (HML, μ -calculus, MCL); model checking; modelling of real-time systems through timed automata; model-based testing. Tools such as CADP and UPPAAL were showcased in lab sessions.

Other academic activities

Reviewing activity.....

I have served as a reviewer or sub-reviewer for the following conferences and journals:

- International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS)
- International Symposium on Formal Methods (FM)
- International Conference on Software Technologies (ICSOFT)
- International Conference on Software Engineering and Formal Methods (SEFM)

- Science of Computer Programming, Elsevier
- Theoretical Aspects of Software Engineering Conference (TASE)

Participation to PhD schools.....

1st VMCAI Winter School

Lisbon, Portugal *January 2019*

The school featured lectures on several topics associated with the VMCAI conference series, including: abstract interpretation (Patrick Cousot, New York University); computing with SAT oracles (João Marques-Silva, University of Lisbon); neural network verification (M. Pawan Kumar, University of Oxford); verification of distributed protocols (Ken McMillan, Microsoft Research).

Invited presentations

- Multi-agent (smart) systems with virtual stigmergies. Kickoff meeting of Italian national research project (PRIN) IT MATTERS: Methods and Tools for Trustworthy Smart Systems. Pisa, Italy, 14 October 2019.
- o *Multi-agent systems with virtual stigmergies*. Invited presentation at IMT School for Advanced Studies. Lucca, Italy, 3 July 2018.

Skills

Technical skills: My experience in programming spans more than a decade. As of now my languages of choice are mainly F# and Python, but I have worked with a number of popular languages across the years (e.g., C, C++, C#, Erlang, Go, Java, Prolog). I have some knowledge of control theory, computer architectures, assembly languages, and hardware description languages (mainly VHDL). I am also familiar with version control systems such as Git and Subversion.

Language skills: Italian is my first language. I am fluent in English (CEFR level C1–C2) and have some knowledge of French (CEFR level A2–B1).

Soft skills: Having been the main contributor to all my publications so far, I have acquired good academic writing skills, as well as an ability to work in groups, meet deadlines, and present my ideas both to my team mates and to external audiences.

Publications

Journal articles.....

Luca Di Stefano, Rocco De Nicola, and Omar Inverso. 2021. "Verification of Distributed Systems via Sequential Emulation". In: *TOSEM*. To appear.Rocco De Nicola, Luca Di Stefano, and Omar Inverso. 2020. "Multi-Agent Systems with Virtual Stigmergy". In: *Sci. Comput. Program*. 187.

Rocco De Nicola, Luca Di Stefano, and Omar Inverso. 2018. "Toward Formal Models and Languages for Verifiable Multi-Robot Systems". In: *Front. Robot. AI* 5.

Peer-reviewed conference and workshop papers.....

Luca Di Stefano and Frédéric Lang. 2021. "Verifying temporal properties of stigmergic collective systems using CADP". In: *ISoLA*.

Luca Di Stefano, Frédéric Lang, and Wendelin Serwe. 2020. "Combining SLiVER with CADP to Analyze Multi-agent Systems". In: *COORDINA-TION*.

Rocco De Nicola, Luca Di Stefano, and Omar Inverso. 2018. "Multi-Agent Systems with Virtual Stigmergy". In: *STAF Workshops*.

Citation indices.....

Accessed on Scopus on January 17, 2022.

Citations: 16 *h*-index: 3

Received research grants

o "Verification of Emerging Properties in Collective Adaptive Systems". Short-term grant, December 2019 – October 2020, IMT Lucca, Italy (see page 2).

References

For references, please contact:

- Rocco De Nicola, Professor of Computer Science, IMT School for Advanced Studies, Lucca, Italy. E-mail: rocco.denicola@imtlucca.it
- Omar Inverso, Assistant Professor, Gran Sasso Science Institute, L'Aquila, Italy. E-mail: omar.inverso@gssi.it
- Frédéric Lang, Research Fellow, Inria and LIG, Montbonnot Saint-Martin, Grenoble, France. E-mail: frederic.lang@inria.fr
- Radu Mateescu, Research Director, Inria and LIG, Montbonnot Saint-Martin, Grenoble, France. E-mail: radu.mateescu@inria.fr

Rocco De Nicola and Omar Inverso supervised my PhD thesis from 2017 to 2020. Frédéric Lang is a permanent member of the CONVECS research team (led by Radu Mateescu), where I worked as a post-doctoral researcher from 2020 to 2022.